Chapter 73.
Stub and Flask kill a right whale, and then have a talk over him.
It must be borne in mind that all this time we have a sperm whale's prodigious
head hanging to the Peekquad's side, but we must let it continue hanging there
for a while till we can get a chance to attend to it. For the present other
matters press, and the best we can do now for the head is to pray heaven the
tackles may hold. Now during the past night and for noon, the Peekquat had
gradually drifted into a sea which by its occasional patches of yellow brit
gave unusual tokens of the vicinity of right whales, a species of the Leviathan
that but few supposed to be at this particular time lurking anywhere near.
And though all hands commonly disdained the capture of those inferior creatures,
and though the Peekquad was not commissioned to cruise for them at all,
and though she had passed numbers of them near the Croettes without lowering
a boat, yet now that a sperm whale had been brought alongside and beheaded, to
the surprise of all, the announcement was made that a right whale should be
captured that day, if opportunity offered. Nor was this long wanting. Tall
spouts were seen to lured, and two boats, stubs and flasks, were detached
in pursuit. Pulling further and further away, they at last became almost
invisible to the men at the mast head.
But suddenly, in the distance they saw a great heap of tumultuous white water,
and soon after news came from a loft that one or both the boats must be fast.
An interval passed and the boats were in plain sight in the act of being dragged
right towards the ship by the towing whale. So close did the monster come to
the hull that at first it seemed as if he meant it malice, but suddenly going
down in a maelstrom within three rods of the planks, he wholly disappeared from
view as if diving under the keel. "Cut, cut!" was the cry from the ship to the
boats, which for one instant seemed on the point of being brought with a deadly
dash against the vessel's side. But having plenty of line yet in the tubs,
and the whale not sounding very rapidly, they paid out abundance of rope, and at
the same time pulled with all their might so as to get ahead of the ship.
For a few minutes the struggle was intensely critical, for while they still
slacked out the tightened line in one direction and still plied their orars in
another, the contending strain threatened to take them under. But it
was only a few feet advance they sought to gain, and they stuck to it till they
did gain it, when instantly a swift tremor was felt running like lightning
along the keel, as the strained line scraping beneath the ship suddenly rose
to view under her boughs, snapping and quivering, and so flinging off its
drippings that the drops fell like bits of broken glass on the water, while the
whale beyond also rose to sight, and once more the boats were free to high.
But the whale abated his speed, and blindly altering his course, went
round the stern of the ship, towing the two boats after him, so that they
performed a complete circuit.
Meanwhile, they hauled more and more upon their lines, till close flanking
him on both sides, Stub answered Flask with lance for lance, and thus round and
round the Peekquad the battle went, while the multitudes of sharks that had
before swam round the sperm whale's body rushed to the fresh blood that was
spilled, thirstily drinking at every new gash, as the eager Israelites did at the
new bursting fountains that poured from the smitten rock. At last his spout grew
thick, and with a frightful roll and vomit, he turned upon his back a corpse.
While the two headsmen were engaged in making fast cords to his flukes, and in
other ways getting the mass in readiness for towing, some conversation ensued
between them. I wonder what the old man wants with this lump of foul lard, said
Stub. Not without some disgust at the thought of having to do with so ignoble a Leviathan.
Once with it, said Flask, coiling some spare line in the boat's bow. Did you
never hear that the ship, which but once has a sperm whale's head hoisted on her
starboard side, and at the same time a right whale's head on the larird, did
you never hear, stub, that that ship can never afterwards capsize? Why not? I
don't know, but I heard that gamboge ghost of a fidala saying so, and he
seems to know all about ship's charms, but I sometimes think he'll charm the
ship to no good at last. I don't half like that, Chapstub. Did you ever notice
how that tusk of his is a sort of carved into a snake's head stub? Sink him. I
never look at him at all. But if ever I
get a chance of a dark night and he's standing hard by the bull works and no
one by. Look down there. Flask pointing into the sea with a peculiar motion of
both hands. I will I flask. I take that fidala to be the devil in disguise. Do
you believe that and bull story about his having been stowed away on
board ship? He's the devil. I say the reason why you don't see his tail is
because he tucks it up out of sight. He carries it coiled away in his pocket. I
guess blast him. Now that I think of it, he's always wanting oak to stuff into
the toes of his boots.
He sleeps in his boots, don't he? He hasn't got any hammock, but I've seen
him lay of nights in a coil of rigging.
No doubt. And it's because of his cursed tail. He coils it down, do you see? In
the eye of the rigging. What's the old man have so much to do with him for?
Striking up a swap or a bargain, I suppose. Bargain about what? Why do you
see the old man is hard bent after that white whale and the devil there is
trying to come round him and get him to swap away his silver watch or his soul
or something of that sort and then he'll surrender Moby Dick
Stub you are skylarking how can Fidala do that I don't know flask but the devil
is a curious chap and a wicked one I
tell you why they say is how he went uh sauntering into the old flagship once
switching his tail Hale about devilish easy and gentlemanlike and inquiring if
the old governor was at home. Well, he was at home and asked the devil what he
wanted. The devil switching his hoofs up and says, "I want John." "What for?"
says the old governor. "What business is that of yours?" says the devil, getting
mad. I want to use him. Take him, says the governor. and by the Lord flask. If
the devil didn't give Jon the Asiatic chalera before he got through with him,
I'll eat this whale in one mouthpull.
But look sharp. Ain't you already there?
Well, then pull ahead and let's get the whale alongside.
I think I remember some such story as you were telling, said Flask, when at
last the two boats were slowly advancing with their burden towards the ship, but
I can't remember where. Three Spaniards, Adventures of Those three Bloody-minded
Soladados. Did you read it there, Flask?
I guess you did. No. Never saw such a book. Heard of it, though. But now tell
me, Stub, do you suppose that that devil you were speaking of just now? Was the
same you say is now on board the Peekquad? Am I the same man that helped
kill this whale? Doesn't the devil live forever? Who ever heard that the devil
was dead? Did you ever see any parson wearing a mourning for the devil? And if
the devil has a latch key to get into the admiral's cabin, don't you suppose
he can crawl into a port hole? Tell me that, Mr. Flask. How old do you suppose
Fidala is? Stub. Do you see that main mass there? Pointing to the ship. Well,
that's the figure one. Now take all the hoops in the peekquad's hold and string
along in a row with that mast or as do you see? Well, that wouldn't begin to be
Fidala's age, nor all the Coopers in creation couldn't show hoops enough to
make as enough. But see here, Stub, I thought you a little boasted just now
that you meant to give Fidala a sea toss if you got a good chance. Now, if he's
so old as all those hoops of yours come to, and if he is going to live forever,
what good will it do to pitch him overboard? Tell me that.
Give him a good ducking anyhow. But he'd crawl back. Duck him again and keep
ducking him. Suppose he should take it into his head to duck you, though. Yes,
and drown you. What then? I should like to see him try it. I'd give him such a
pair of black eyes that he wouldn't dare show his face in the admiral's cabin
again for a long while, let alone down in the orop there where he lives, and
hereabouts on the upper decks where he sneaks so much. Damn the devil, flasp.
So, you suppose I'm afraid of the devil?
Who's afraid of him except the old governor who daresn't catch him and put
him in double derbies as he deserves, but lets him go about kidnapping people.
I signed a bond with him that all the people the devil kidnapped, he'd roast
for him. There's a governor. Do you suppose Fidala wants to kidnap Captain
Ahab? Do I suppose it? You'll know it before long, Flask. But I am going now
to keep a sharp lookout on him. And if I see anything very suspicious going on,
I'll just take him by the nape of the neck and say, "Look here, Beelbub. You
don't do it." And if he makes any fuss by the lord, I'll make a grab into his
pocket for his tail. Take it to the capston and give him such a wrenching
and heaving that his tail will come short off at the stump. You see? And
then I rather guess when he finds himself docked in that queer fashion,
he'll sneak off without the poor satisfaction of feeling his tail between
his legs. And what will you do with the tail, Stub? Do with it? Sell it for an
ox whip when we get home. What else?
Now, do you mean what you say and have been saying all along, Stub? Mean or not
mean, here we are at the ship.
The boats were here hailed to tow the whale on the larbird side where fluke
chains and other necessaries were already prepared for securing him.
Didn't I tell you so? said Flask. Yes, you'll soon see this right whale's head
hoisted up opposite that Parmesetes.
In good time Flask's saying proved true.
As before, the Peekquad steeply leaned over towards the sperm whale's head. Now
by the counterpoise of both heads she regained her even keel though sorely
strained you may well believe. So when on one side you hoist in locks head you
go over that way but now on the other side hoist in K and you come back again
but in very poor plight. Thus some mines forever keep trimming boat. Oh you
foolish. throw all these thunderheads overboard and then you will float light and right.
In disposing of the body of a right whale when brought alongside the ship,
the same preliminary proceedings commonly take place as in the case of a
sperm whale. Only in the latter instance, the head is cut off whole, but
in the former, the lips and tongue are separately removed and hoisted on deck
with all the well-known black bone attached to what is called the crown
piece. But nothing like this in the present case had been done. The
carcasses of both whales had dropped a stern, and the headladen ship not a
little resembled a mule, carrying a pair of overburdening piurs.
Meanwhile, Fidala was calmly eyeing the right whale's head, and ever and anon
glancing from the deep wrinkles there to the lines in his own hand. And Ahab
chanced so to stand that the Parsy occupied his shadow, while if the Parsy
shadow was there at all, it seemed only to blend with and lengthen Ahabs. As the
crew toiled on, laplandish speculations were bandied among them concerning all
these passing things.